<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-01-10T06:10:36+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Practical Guide to Using the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph in (your) Research</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-poster/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Practical Guide to Using the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph in (your) Research"/><published>2022-07-13T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-13T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-poster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-poster/"><![CDATA[<p>Scientific articles are mostly published as text files containing unstructured and semi-structured information. Consequently, important information is typically deeply hidden in documents which severely limits the possibilities to automatically process and reuse scholarly knowledge. One approach to make information explicit and directly usable is to transform this into a standardised format and store it in a knowledge graph. This allows scholarly knowledge to be represented in a structured, machine-actionable, interlinked and semantically rich manner. The EBRAINS Knowledge Graph was developed to facilitate the search and information exchange in research, so that research results across different domains become directly comparable and easier to retrieve and reuse.</p> <p>Here, we provide a practical guide to extracting information from the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph using a user-friendly interface as well as a more advanced programmatic route via an Application Programming Interface (API). We also provide concrete examples on how the extracted information can be leveraged in order to develop new research objectives as well as validate ongoing research. The EBRAINS Knowledge Graph is integrated in the wider EBRAINS research infrastructure as a part of the EBRAINS Data and Knowledge services for sharing and finding research data and models. Data found through these services can be directly used and analysed via the various integrated tools and analysis workflows. The EBRAINS Knowledge Graph is a valuable machine-actionable and FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable) resource for discovery-based and hypothesis-driven research as it already contains a wide variety of neuroscience data types, models and software.</p> <p>Access the user examples <a href="https://wiki.ebrains.eu/bin/view/Collabs/fens-2022-poster-examples">here</a> and Try It Yourself!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/FENS2022_KnowledgeGraph_MaaikeVanSwieten-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/FENS2022_KnowledgeGraph_MaaikeVanSwieten-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/FENS2022_KnowledgeGraph_MaaikeVanSwieten-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/FENS2022_KnowledgeGraph_MaaikeVanSwieten.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talks"/><category term="Talks"/><category term="Conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Poster presentation at FENS 2022]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making the most of precious data - challenges and opportunities in mining open data</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-talk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making the most of precious data - challenges and opportunities in mining open data"/><published>2022-07-12T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-12T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/fens-talk/"><![CDATA[<p>Together with fellow experts in the field, Mathew Birdsall Abrams and Stephanie Albin, I had the pleasure to share my perspectives on the road to effective data mining in the Special Interest Event “Making the most of precious data: challenges and opportunities in mining open data” at FENS 2022.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/FENS2022_DataMining_MaaikeVanSwieten-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/FENS2022_DataMining_MaaikeVanSwieten-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/FENS2022_DataMining_MaaikeVanSwieten-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/FENS2022_DataMining_MaaikeVanSwieten.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The aim of this session is to explore and identify the challenges and opportunities facing researchers who wish to better utilise or mine neuroscience and clinical data sets already available. Modern neuroscience and clinical methods generate huge amounts of data in a wide array of formats. Few laboratories, however, are effectively sharing or reusing data. This session will touch on how to create an environment conducive to data sharing and reuse. In addition, data must be findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (FAIR) to allow secondary analysis to generate new insights from existing data sets.</p> <p>My presentation is also featured on the <a href="https://www.humanbrainproject.eu/en/follow-hbp/news/2022/07/19/making-most-precious-data-experts-weigh-neuroscience-data-sharing/?utm_source=linkedin&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_campaign=fens_data_panel">Human Brain Project website</a></p> <p>Slides are available here: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6832317">DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.6832317</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talks"/><category term="Talks"/><category term="Conferences"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Invited Talk and Panel Discussion at FENS 2022 (Special Interest Event)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Small Data Big - Building a graph database from experimental brain research</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/nature-webcast/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Small Data Big - Building a graph database from experimental brain research"/><published>2022-06-27T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-27T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/nature-webcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2022/nature-webcast/"><![CDATA[<p>The sharing of research data is essential to ensure reproducibility and maximise the impact of scientific research. Data sharing also has many benefits for researchers, including contributing to career advancement, acquiring new funding, or meeting requirements of journals.</p> <p>The EBRAINS Data and Knowledge services are based in the principle that, for the greatest impact, data should be shared in a FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable) manner, and offers support to neuroscientists in preparing data and metadata for sharing.</p> <p>These services, co-funded by the European Commission and national funding bodies, are a collaborative effort of six research institutions across Europe that are coordinated by the EBRAINS Norwegian node at the University of Oslo.</p> <p>This webcast will provide user examples of the data sharing process as well as tangible examples of how information stored in the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph can be extracted and leveraged to develop new research objectives and validate ongoing research.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/big-data-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/big-data-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/big-data-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/big-data.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>This webcast is intended for researchers and anyone who is interested in learning more about sharing and reusing neuroscience research data, models or software.</p> <p>Learn how to:</p> <ul> <li>Find and access data and metadata from the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph</li> <li>Use data from the EBRAINS Knowledge Graph in new research</li> <li>Share your own data through the EBRAINS Data and Knowledge services</li> </ul> <p>Register for free to watch the webcast <a href="https://www.workcast.com/register?cpak=2852116575245769&amp;referrer=WEBCASTHOMEPAGE_EBRAINS_OSLO_0622">on demand</a></p> <p>Slides are available here: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6839215">DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.6839215</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talks"/><category term="Talks"/><category term="Video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nature Portfolio Webcast]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to make data public - ethics, regulations and solutions</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/ethics-talk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to make data public - ethics, regulations and solutions"/><published>2021-12-10T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-10T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/ethics-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/ethics-talk/"><![CDATA[<p>The amount of Health Data being generated is on the rise. Yet, the sharing of medical data is lagging. Although there are many tangible advantages of making health data available, such as leveraging data to enable the early detection of brain diseases, many people are concerned that health data might be misused.</p> <p>The EAN-EBRAINS workshop encourages open discussions on issues and challenges associated with medical data sharing in Clinical Neuroscience in Europe.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/types-of-datasets-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/types-of-datasets-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/types-of-datasets-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/types-of-datasets.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>For more information about the EAN-EBRAINS workshop, <a href="https://www.humanbrainproject.eu/en/education/ebrains-workshops/medicaldata/">click here</a> Slides are available here: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6380142">DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.6380142</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZHLKp2kaQwg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talks"/><category term="Talks"/><category term="Video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talk at the EAN-EBRAINS Joint Workshop - The Future of Medical Data Sharing in Clinical Neurosciences]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A day in the life of a data curator</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/day-as-curator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A day in the life of a data curator"/><published>2021-11-11T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-11T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/day-as-curator</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/day-as-curator/"><![CDATA[<p>The data review process provides an essential service to our community by supporting researchers with the curation, sharing, access, and long-term preservation of their data</p> <blockquote> <p>“Every data and software submission is thoroughly reviewed to check the validity of the [meta]data and to ensure quality requirements of the repository are met.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Proper data curation enables datasets to be more easily found, understood and reused to benefit wider society. Our repository provides an intuitive infrastructure that allows researchers to discover, download and reuse data to avoid duplication of time and effort spent unnecessarily creating new datasets.</p> <h2 id="data-organisation">Data Organisation</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/data-organisation-key-points-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/data-organisation-key-points-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/data-organisation-key-points-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/data-organisation-key-points.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>File format, documentation (data descriptor (is partly also the metadata)), privacy aspects. Do the data files contain personally identifiable, sensitive or inappropriate information? Depending on the type of data, we need to add extra layers of security. Content: do the data match the metadata that is provided and does it match the scope of EBRAINS.</p> <h2 id="metadata-organisation">Metadata organisation</h2> <p>Data providers are asked to provide metadata regarding the dataset as well as the individual subjects that were used for the study. Information about title, description, experimental approaches, keywords, type of dataset, funding, related publications, licence, techniques, subjects, and protocols. Type of file format is reported so that it can be linked to software. This allows third parties to more easily access the data. In addition to security for identifiable data, we also allow researchers to put their data under temporary embargo until their research is published. This makes the metadata visible, so that the dataset can be cited, but the data is hidden until the manuscript is published providing extra security to the researchers.</p> <h2 id="communication-with-the-data-provider">Communication with the data provider</h2> <p>As soon as the data providers submits a request for curation, the preliminary information about the dataset is sent to the review board. They assess whether the dataset falls within the scope of EBRAINS. Then the dataset is assigned to one of the curators who will contact the data provider for a statement on the ethics status of the research study and for filling out additional metadata. The metadata is integrated into the knowledge graph, relying on controlled terms and ontologies, and following the metadata structure openMINDS. The standardised vocabularies and metadata allow us to link related datasets to each other.</p> <p>Typically, the interaction with data providers is limited to a handful of email exchanges, starting with the request to provide metadata and finishing with the approval of the data and metadata integration into the knowledge graph before the dataset is released for publication.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The data review process provides an essential service to our community by supporting researchers with the curation, sharing, access, and long-term preservation of their data]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Open data in neuroscience - Data sharing in EBRAINS</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/incf-course/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open data in neuroscience - Data sharing in EBRAINS"/><published>2021-10-01T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/incf-course</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/incf-course/"><![CDATA[<p>There is a general consensus among researchers, publishers and funding bodies that data sharing could tackle major reproducibility and transparency challenges that currently exist in the field of neuroscience. However, making your data open is not enough! To increase the Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability and Reuse potential of research, data needs to integrated properly. EBRAINS has developed standards and best practices to ensure that you will get the most out of data sharing; increased exposure of your research and credit in the form of citations.</p> <p>In this course, we walk you through the curation process from start to finish and introduce you to workflows, integrated analysis pipelines and tools that can further research for yourself and others!</p> <p>Course features:</p> <ul> <li>What is open data?</li> <li>Data sharing through EBRAINS</li> <li>How to prepare your data and how to increase the FAIRness of your data</li> </ul> <p>Check out the course on the <a href="https://training.incf.org/course/open-data-neuroscience-data-sharing-ebrains">INCF Training Space</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zZcBWgo3Nno" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tCrVAqH1MDs" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Courses"/><category term="Video"/><category term="Talks"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Course on the INCF training space]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Publishing and Accessing Research through EBRAINS</title><link href="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/mesec-talk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Publishing and Accessing Research through EBRAINS"/><published>2021-09-07T10:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-07T10:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/mesec-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maaikevs.github.io/blog/2021/mesec-talk/"><![CDATA[<p>n September 2021, 16 early-career researchers from diverse backgrounds came together to share ideas and discuss current developments related to the topic of consciousness. These discussions were followed by presentations about the EBRAINS research infrastructure and the use of their tools and services.</p> <p>I was invited to give an introduction into the Data and Knowledge service of the EBRAINS research infrastructure. This service supports researchers in sharing and finding data, models and software.</p> <p>Despite the session being online, it could still be an interactive session with the use of interactive polls.</p> <p>What I found out about the attendees was that 50% of the people had shared data or code before. Of the remaining 50%, 80% would be interested in sharing data in the future. There are many reasons to share data, for example to comply with data sharing policies of journals. Interestingly, the majority of the attendees of this talk indicated that they think data should be shared to improve reproducibility (60%), followed by to encourage reuse (30%).</p> <p>When talking about data sharing we typically also mention the FAIR principles. The FAIR principles focus on making data findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable and emphasise machine-actionability. Only 30% of the attendees had heard of the FAIR principles before, which is similar to the 28% reported in the 2021 State of OpenData report by Digital Science. The number of researchers familiar with the FAIR principles has been steadily growing over the last 5 years, this number is still quite low. Machine-actionability can only be achieved if metadata (information that accompanies data) is provided in a format that can be read and used by machines. However, ‘human-readable’ metadata is equally important and should therefore not be omitted.</p> <p>The video of this talk is available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ocrM9tzIPgI&quot;">YouTube</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ocrM9tzIPgI" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talks"/><category term="Talks"/><category term="Video"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talk at the Mediterranean seminar for consciousness]]></summary></entry></feed>